Hi everyone, today's lecture is
going to focus on how the use of
large language models, or LLMs, for
structured data extraction in a way
that's methodologically defensible.
So the most important phrase today
is going to be "assistance, not
automation." We're not treating LLMs
as autonomous decision makers. We're
treating them as tools embedded
inside a structured
measurement pipeline.
So the lecture is about turning
messy, unstructured text into
analysis, structured data, while
preserving transparency,
replicability, and validity.
So many social science data sets
that originally are from things like
archival documents, news articles,
legal filings, speeches,
transcripts,
reports, and social media.
These sources are often messy.
There's formatting that's going to
vary. They're unstructured. They're
not already in rows or columns.
They're text-heavy, so they have
long narratives rather
than discrete variables.
And they're
expensive to code manually.
Traditional hand coding is slow,
costly, and difficult to scale. And
often undergraduate coders
are also very unreliable.
So LLMs can provide things like
rapid text parsing, pattern
recognition, information extraction,
and instruction output generation.
But they do not provide truth.
So they provide probabilistic
outputs based on training data. So
the methodological shift is this.
We're going to use LLMs to scale
extraction, but we designed
workflows to detect incorrect error.
So what's human-in-the-loop
philosophy? Let's define it.
Human-in-the-loop systems are
workflows in which AI generates
provisional outputs. Humans monitor,
validate, and
override these outputs.
The system routes uncertainty back
to human judgment.
So in this course, LLMs are used to
propose structured outputs. They're
going to accelerate your labeling.
And when we have cases of
uncertainty, we're going to flag it
so that humans are
responsible for the validation.
So humans are going to be then, in
this case, responsible for a final
validation, schema design, error
detection, and then
theoretical interpretation.
The human is going to be accountable
for the measurement. The LLM is
basically seen as a
fast, fallible system.
So now let's define the core
concept, structured extraction.
Structured extraction is going to
mean you're going to
define a schema in advance.
You're going to constrain outputs
into fixed fields, and you're going
to reject freeform narrative output.
So what is a schema? A schema is a
predefined structure that specifies
variable names, data times,
permissible values,
and format constraints.
So an example of this would be,
instead of asking what happened in
this article, you ask to extract the
actor, the action, the
target, and the date.
So the schema's disciplined model
behavior, without a schema, the
model improvises. With the schema,
the model fills structured slots.
This dramatically improves
consistency and auditability.
So let's take a look
at a schema example.
We have our actor, which is a
string, our action within a string,
the target of that action, the date,
and the confidence for it.
So the actor, in this case, would be
like an entity performing the
action. The action would be a verb
describing the behavior.
The target would be the recipient of
that actor. The date is going to be
a standardized temporal format, and
the confidence is going to be the
model reported on a certain date.
So why do we include confidence?
Because uncertainty
must become measurable.
So explicit schemas reduce ambiguity
in three ways. They reduce the
interpretive drift, they enable
automated validation, and they make
downstream analysis tractable.
So if the alpha is not valid JSON,
the pipeline is going to reject it.
So how do we find prompt design? A
prompt is not just instructions,
it's the part of the
measurement instrument.
So effective extraction prompts are
going to describe the task narrowly.
They're going to specify the exact
output format. They're going to
include examples, if it's possible,
and they're going to
find abstention behavior.
So prompting is part of that method.
If two researchers use different
prompts, they are measuring
different things.
Therefore, prompts must be version
controlled,
documented, and reproducible.
So this is a prompt example here. We
have extract the following fields
from the text below, and then return
a JSON match in the schema.
I showed an example previously where
we have the actor, the action, the
target, the date, and
the confidence on it.
So notice what this is going to do
together. It's going to force a
structure in it. It's going to
eliminate narrative prose.
It's going to constrain our
formatting, and it's going to enable
a machine validation.
So if the model outputs invalid
JSON, we're going to get an
automatic failure, and then a brief
prompt for you in review.
But this machine checkable outputs
are critical for scale.
So now let's shift from single calls
to scale. When you scale LLM
extraction, you build a pipeline.
Pipelines must manage rate limits,
API failures, token limits, cost
constraints, logging,
and reproducibility.
So scaling is an engineering
problem. Each API call has latency,
monetary costs, and potential error.
So extraction pipelines must retry
failures, log prompts and responses,
track token usage, and handle
malformed outputs.
So let's see what a typical error
might be. We have our results here.
We're iterating over our documents.
We're calling our LLM here, and then
we're appending it. That size is
going to affect the cost and
reliability for it.
So now we define model uncertainty
for it. How do we define this?
Right? So LLMs are going to generate
outputs probabilistically.
They can report confidence scores,
express uncertainty,
abstain, or flag ambiguity.
Uncertainty should be captured
explicitly. So why would we want to
do this? Because
uncertainty is data.
Instead of hiding model output, we
want to actually just measure.
So here's an example of how we might
do this, right? If our response
confidence is less than 0.6, we want
a flag of her view.
So low confidence cases are routed
to humans in this case.
So how do we define validation?
Validation is a process of verifying
that extracted data reflect the
intended concept.
So human review serves two purposes.
We want to spot check our outputs,
identify systematic errors, refine
prompts, and adjust schemas.
Validation can be iterative. The
process can be we're going to run
our extraction, audit a subset of
it, identify failure modes, modify
our schema or
prompt, and then rerun it.
This cycle is central to
defensible measurement.
So what are spot audits? Audit
strategies are going to include
things like random sampling,
stratified sampling, edge case
review, and then
adversarial testing.
Audits do not just estimate error
rates. They're going to
reveal our failure modes.
So for example, models of
hallucinating states when none
exist, models might swamp actor and
target, models might overassign
agent same, and then failure
discovery is going to be part of our
scientific record.
So what are our failure modes?
Common how long failure modes
include things like
hallucinated fields.
Overconfident errors, wrong but with
high certainty.
Formatting drift, so invalid JSON.
Sensitivity to phrasing, so
inconsistent outputs. And failures
must be documented. We want to
maintain a failure along. So what
happened? Why? How often? And what
are our mitigation steps? And this
becomes part of
our methods appendix.
So extraction performance is going
to be evaluated with something
called precision recall. This is
going to be the proportion of
precision is the proportion of
extraction items that are correct.
Recall is going to be the proportion
of true items that are extracted. We
can combine this with something
called an F1 score, which balances
our precision recall metrics.
We want to also use field level
accuracy. This is going to be just
how well it does across different
dimensions for our data.
We want to look at agreement with
human labels. This can be intercoder
or agreement comparisons or
intercoder reliability.
But these are all different ways
that we can evaluate
how well an LM is doing.
So one thing to remember is that LMs
are not neutral. They reflect
training data biases, prompt
framing, and then
default response tendencies.
So they may under identify
marginalized actress, misclassify
ambiguous cases, default to
stereotypical assumptions. So in
these cases, human oversight is as
essential for it.
This is both a technical and ethical
requirement. But one thing to also
keep in mind when we're talking
about LMs assisting with data
extraction is that undergraduate or
graduate coders or whoever is coding
the data really also suffer from
things like biases, prompt framing
issues, and then they maybe do
things like hallucinate as well.
So anyone that's had undergraduate
coders for a large project know that
cases where undergraduates are not
reliable, they're not really paying
attention to what they're doing, and
they're like quickly
going through a coding task.
I've had an experience on a project
that I worked on where an
undergraduate pretended to do a
bunch of work and then arbitrarily
coded and asked to be paid on it.
So that would be an example of like
an undergraduate at code, having
hallucination in this case. So all
of them have these problems, but
they also exist with
human coders as well.
And I think that's especially true
for things that are low skilled
tasks like things that we would
delegate to undergraduates.
So every LLM extraction pipeline has
to record its model name and
version, the exact prompt text, the
schema definition, its batch size,
its validation procedure, its
failure rates, and
its null limitations.
This transparency is useful because
it enables reuse for people who are
going to work on this later. And
without documentation, the data set
cannot be replicated.
So what do we want to emphasize in
practice? For this course test, we
want to use LLMs as assistance,
enforce structure aggressively,
validate with humans,
document our failures.
And if you follow these principles,
you can scale extraction without
sacrificing murder.
So where are LLMs going to help
most? For large text corpora, for
vent extraction, metadata tagging,
first pass coding, and where do they
fail quietly? Things where there's
like ambiguous language, rare
categories, edge cases, context
heavy interpretation.
So how much better, and when we're
doing these things, we want to think
about how much validation is enough.
We want to have enough that our
error rates are estimated, our
failure moves are documented, the
pipeline is transparent.
And when we end up, we want to just
begin, this is assistance, not
automation. So if all ones are
embedded inside a structure,
validated, and document measurement
pipeline, they can meaningfully
increase our productivity without
undermining scientific integrity.